<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author>Neja Blaj Hribar</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-11-22</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2024-01-16T06:55:56Z</date><name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Elementary and middle school</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"> With middle school we refer to
                            the first four years of Gymnasium.</note><hi rend="bold"> textbooks
                        between 1774 and 1918: An annotated bibliography with supporting
                    study</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>1 Introduction</head>
                <p>The present publication provides a comprehensive database of textbooks and
                        related materials intended for or used in practice in classes in primary
                        schools and lower grades of secondary schools between the years 1774 and
                        1918. It was created as part of the work on the project "Schools and
                        Imperial, National, and Transnational Identifications: Habsburg Empire,
                        Yugoslavia, and Slovenia” (J6-2573),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"> The description of the project is available
                            on the website of the Faculty of Arts of the University of Ljubljana:
                                <ref target="https://www.ff.uni-lj.si/sole-in-identifikacije">https://www.ff.uni-lj.si/sole-in-identifikacije</ref> (September
                            11, 2023). </note> which was co-financed by the Slovene Research
                        and Innovation Agency. Neja Blaj Hribar and Jan Bernot, members of the
                        support team, dealt with the collection, classification, and digitization of
                        the material. Members of the project team, including principal investigator
                        Rok Stergar and researchers Karin Almasy, Jernej Kosi, Jovana Mihajlović
                        Trbovc, Tamara Pavasović Trošt, Marko Zajc, and Vita Zalar, also helped us
                        in the design of the database. Oliver Pejić also helped us with many useful
                        tips and comments. We would like to express our sincere gratitude to Karin
                        Almasy for her generous support and the advice and material collected during
                        her research work. We also wish to thank Matej Hriberšek, who kindly shared
                        with us his lists of textbook materials for classical language classes, and
                        Teodor Domej, who also assisted us with his advice.
                </p>
                <p>A digital publication in this form would not have been possible without the
                        collaborators of the infrastructure program at the Institute of Contemporary
                        History. We would like to give particular mention to Mihael Ojsteršek who
                        put everything into its digital form, the students Tamara Logar and Daša
                        Mikuž, and Marko Kupljen and Ana Cvek for digitizing the textbooks and
                        publishing them on the Sistory.si portal.
                </p>
                <p>Further thanks are due to the Slovene School Museum and all the employees of
                        their library, who made it possible for us to borrow and digitize their
                        textbooks.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2 Structure</head>
                <p>Working on the user interface presented us with a considerable challenge in
                        view of the amount and variety of textbook material, as well as the
                        occasional absence or incompleteness of relevant data. Some compromises and
                        simplifications were necessary, which will be explained in more detail in
                        the following lines.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>2.1 Criteria for the selection of textbook material</head>
                    <p>The criteria for the selection of textbooks included in the database were
                            somewhat arbitrary. This applies especially to the beginning of the
                            period in question, when the gap between the prescribed material and the
                            texts that teachers and priests used to teach the youth was often
                            significant. The gap between the prescribed textbooks and everyday
                            practice gradually decreased during the period considered. In textbook
                            material from the second half of the nineteenth century, especially in
                            that which was created after 1869, there are significantly fewer
                            outlined deviations. In the following lines, we will focus further on
                            the criteria we used to classify the textbook material in the
                            database.</p>
                    <p>1. The bibliography is time-bound by the General School Ordinance from
                            1774 and the dissolution of Austria-Hungary in 1918. Naturally, some of
                            the texts that were used in school lessons in the Theresian and
                            Josephinian eras (and often later) were written before 1774. We included
                            such textbooks in the review only where their use in the period after
                            1774 was sufficiently attested in sources and literature. It is,
                            admittedly, possible, and indeed probable, that other older texts were
                            also in use during that period. However, this is still open to further
                            research. Even the year with which we conclude the bibliography was by
                            no means an impenetrable barrier. Quite the contrary! Many textbooks
                            were published in a more or less modified form also in the new state
                            framework.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p> The same
                                    applies to a significant part of the authors of the textbook
                                    material. After the upheaval of 1918, they also generally
                                    continued to work.</p></note> In such cases, we also
                            mention editions from the period after 1918 in the notes.</p>
                    <p>2. The area in question was part of the Habsburg Empire for most of the
                            period under consideration. The exception is the period between 1809 and
                            1813 when parts of these lands were included in the French Illyrian
                            provinces; we included the textbooks published during that era in the
                            bibliography as well.
                    </p>
                    <p>3. Because the research project focused mainly on the development of
                            Slovene nationalism, and due to time and practical limitations, we did
                            not include a significant part of the textbooks and teaching aids in the
                            Latin, German, Italian, Hungarian, and Croatian languages ​​in the
                            database. We are aware that this is why a large part of the textbook
                            material that was in use at major schools (Hauptschulen), normal schools
                            (Normalschulen), and (later) either at so-called utraquist or bilingual
                            elementary schools or at elementary schools (Volksschulen) with German
                            or another language of instruction, and especially at high schools and
                            Realschulen, is missing. In the future – either as a supplement to this
                            publication or as part of further research – this material will
                            undoubtedly need to be analyzed in more detail and included in the
                            present corpus of textbook material. </p>
                    <p>4. The decision to focus in this phase on the collection and
                            classification of textbook material, which came into consideration
                            during compulsory education, is also related to the above limitations.
                            Thus, we focused on textbook material intended for primary
                            schools–primary school, according to the definition used by Bogo
                            Grafenauer in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Slovencev</hi> [History of Slovenes], is
                            understood as "a school which does not require any previous education,
                            educates everyone in their mother tongue and gives them basic knowledge,
                            regardless of their social affiliation and future profession"<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p> Grafenauer, Bogo:
                                    "Podržavljenje šolstva in splošna šolska obveznost." In: 
                                <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Slovencev,</hi> ed. Čepič et al.
                                    Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1979,
                            375.</p></note>–and to lower secondary schools. Textbooks
                            intended for lyceums, high schools,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"> With high school we refer to the latter
                                years of Gymnasium.</note> and Realschulen, as well as
                            materials that were used in teachers training colleges
                            (Lehrerbildungsanstalten) and vocational schools, are therefore not
                            included.
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p> In the future, supplementing
                                    the present collection with material intended for classes in the
                                    above-mentioned institutions would certainly be
                                welcome.</p></note></p>
                    <p>Indeed, the duration of compulsory education in the period in question
                            was anything but stable, thus the decisions regarding the inclusion and
                            exclusion of textbook material are always at least somewhat arbitrary.
                            Compulsory education was initially limited to the period between the
                            ages of six and twelve years by the General School Ordinance from
                            1774.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">Schmidt, Vlado:
                                    <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike na
                                    Slovenskem I. (Od naselitve do 1805).</hi> Ljubljana:
                                    Delavska enotnost, 1988, 180.
                            </note>
                        Even if there was no compulsory education in the Illyrian provinces, we
                            took into account textbook material intended for schooling at the
                            primary and (at least) lower secondary level for this short-term
                            intermezzo – in addition to the textbook material intended for the newly
                            formed uniform four-year primary schools – for the sake of a relatively
                            manageable corpus of material and in the face of sudden changes in the
                            field of secondary education<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p>
                                Šumrada, Janez: "Poglavitne poteze napoleonske politike v
                                    Ilirskih provincah,"
                                <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 61, No. 1–2 (2007):
                                    81–83.</p></note>. After the restoration of Habsburg
                            power, the school system on the territory of the former Illyrian
                            provinces was restored to its previous state. With the decree of the
                            Study Court Commission of September 27, 1816, compulsory education was
                            extended and ended with the completion of fifteen years of age, whereby
                            in the newly added period, as Schmidt points out, "only Sunday lessons
                            were obligatory."
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p> Schmidt, Vlado: <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike na Slovenskem II.
                                    (1805–1848).</hi> Ljubljana: Državna založba Slovenije,
                                    1964, 132.</p></note> With the liberal school reform in
                            1869, the tendency towards a general eight-year compulsory school
                            attendance came into force. The ideal of eight-year compulsory education
                            was fully implemented only in Styria and Carinthia, but not entirely in
                            the other provinces included in this bibliography. The right to shorten
                            compulsory school attendance was given to:</p>
                    <p>– Princely County of Gorizia and Gradisca, where the provincial school
                            board was allowed to "shorten compulsory education to five years (from
                            completed age of seven years to completed age of twelve years) in those
                            school districts where local conditions would require it";
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p> Schmidt, Vlado: <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike na Slovenskem III.
                                    (1848–1870).</hi> Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost, 1988,
                                    195.
                            </p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>– Istria, which opted for a "six-year compulsory education (from
                            completed age of six years to completed age of twelve years) with review
                            school (Wiederholungsschule) in the winter to the completed age of
                            fourteen years";
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p> Ibid,
                            195–96.</p></note></p>
                    <p>– Carniola, where compulsory education was determined by the Law on how
                            to regulate the management, maintenance, and attendance of elementary
                            schools, as follows: "The duty to go to school (school duty) starts from
                            the age of six and lasts, as a rule, until the age of twelve, and until
                            the age of fourteen in cities and towns with schools that have three or
                            more classes. With regard to special local circumstances or the climate,
                            the district school authority may exceptionally allow that school duty
                            begins only after the completed age of 7 or 8 years. In the same manner,
                            the district school authority may allow children who have reached the
                            age of twelve years and have completely learned their school subjects to
                            be dismissed from school in cities and towns as well".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p> Ibid, 200; Deželni zakonik za
                                    vojvodstvo kranjsko 25, No. 8 (26. 06. 1873): 57.
                            </p></note> In Carniola, the outlined changes were implemented only
                            in 1873, and in 1870 in the remaining provinces included in our
                            bibliography.
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p> Schmidt: <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike na Slovenskem
                                    III.</hi>, 196.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.2 Authors, co-authors, translators, and editors</head>
                    <p>Especially in the earlier period, the records of authors' names and
                            surnames were often inconsistent. In different editions of the same
                            textbook or different textbooks by the same author, we often have to
                            deal with different records of the authors' names and surnames. To a
                            certain extent this is the result of changes in transcription, and
                            partly the result of a decision to write the name in another language.
                            It also happens that the author, to whom the authorship of the textbook
                            can be attributed with a considerable degree of certainty based on
                            sources and existing research, is not even mentioned in the textbook.
                            Since strictly following the original inscriptions in each textbook
                            would therefore cause unnecessary confusion and make it difficult for
                            the user to perform a search, we have always used the standard version
                            of the name and surname records. In doing so, we relied in particular on
                            Slovene Biographical Lexicon and the Slovene library information system
                            Cobiss as well as other relevant literature on the subject.</p>
                    <p>In addition, for the sake of transparency, we listed the original authors
                            separately – field: "Original author (if it is an adaptation) / Author
                            (if it is an original work)" – and authors of later adaptations,
                            translators, and editors – field: "Author of the adaptation / Translator
                            / Editor." It must be pointed out in this regard that the distinction
                            between the author of the original and the adapter is not always
                            completely unambiguous. Some textbooks were published for a very long
                            period of time. In such cases, the many rewritings of the textbook (many
                            of which were created even after the death of the original author) could
                            be regarded as an independent work without any particular reservations,
                            and the author of the adaptation could be considered an author in the
                            true sense of the word. Indeed, such decisions are always at least
                            somewhat arbitrary. In order to avoid inconsistency, we decided on an
                            approach according to which, even in cases of major revisions, we kept
                            all later editions of a textbook in the same entry – in cases where we
                            decided otherwise, we explained our decision to treat the textbook
                            independently in the notes. Since numerous textbooks are translations,
                            we have always listed translators in addition to the original author.
                            The line between editor and author is often blurred. Especially in the
                            case of readers and songbooks, the individual cited as the author was
                            often not the author of the selected texts, but only a sort of editor.
                            We only mentioned the editors in exceptional cases, when they were
                            listed next to the author.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.3 Titles<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p> When
                                    transliterating titles from the Dajnko alphabet (dajnčica), the
                                    Metelko alphabet (metelčica), and the Bohorič alphabet
                                    (bohoričica), we followed the records on Cobiss and dLib. We are
                                    aware that the transliteration method on both websites is often
                                    inadequate (at this point we would like to thank Teodor Domej,
                                    who has drawn our attention to the matter), but in order to make
                                    it easier to search for material in various databases, we have
                                    decided not to change these
                        transliterations.</p></note></head>
                    <p>In the field "Title (first edition)" we indicate the title of the first
                            edition, or if this is unknown, the title of the first edition for which
                            we have accurate title information. In some cases, it happens that we
                            know from the reports of contemporaries that the textbook was published
                            earlier, but the first edition has not been preserved. At times it also
                            happens that otherwise reliable sources, which talk about the textbook
                            being published, do not contain information about the exact title. In
                            such cases, we did not specify approximate titles. We have consistently
                            adhered to the principle of keeping the title record – if at all
                            possible – in its original form. Since the year is always added to the
                            title, the reader will easily find out whether it is the title of the
                            first edition or the first known edition of the textbook.</p>
                    <p>We list the known titles of all subsequent editions in the field "Title
                            (subsequent editions)." Even in this case, it often happens that we know
                            for sure that it existed – in this case, mostly based on the mentions of
                            the previous, inaccessible editions at the beginning of one of the
                            textbooks that we had at our disposal. Therefore, in some parts there is
                            a discrepancy between the number of years indicated in the field "Year
                            (later editions)" and the years that are written in parentheses next to
                            the different versions of the title. In this case also we have always
                            tried to preserve the original format of the title. Years in parentheses
                            refer to editions with the same title.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.4 Places of publication
                    </head>
                    <p>Records of places of publication underwent many changes during the period
                            considered. In part, it is a consequence of the absence or insufficient
                            standardization of the language in which the textbooks used in the area
                            considered were written. This is further complicated by the fact that
                            the place was often written in Latin, German or some other language. In
                            order for the present bibliography to be sufficiently transparent and,
                            more importantly, to enable the user to use the database more
                            efficiently, we have used the modern English versions of place names at
                            all times. </p>
                    <p>In the field "Place (first edition)" we indicate the place of the first
                            known edition. Locations of all other editions are indicated in the
                            field "Place (later editions)". In relation to writing years in
                            parentheses, the same rules apply as when listing titles.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.5 Publishers</head>
                    <p>Changes and inconsistencies are even more pronounced when listing
                            publishers than when listing place names. Standardization was necessary
                            in this case as well. We realize that the way the name of the publisher
                            was written (the same applies to the place name) is important and as
                            such could be the subject of historiographical analysis, but in this
                            case, ease of use prevailed over any such concerns. What is more, such a
                            decision was also a consequence of the fact that we often relied on
                            entries in the Cobiss library information system due to the abundance of
                            material. Although the entries on the aforementioned system generally
                            preserve the original notation, standardization still occurred, so that
                            the recording of the original form of the publisher's name would not
                            always be possible in any case. When standardizing, we mostly followed
                            the record found in the Slovene Biographical Lexicon; when dealing with
                            earlier periods we relied principally on the work of Anja Dular, Vlado
                            Schmidt, and Ivan Andoljšek.
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">Dular,
                                Anja: <hi rend="italic">Živeti od knjig: zgodovina knjigotrštva na
                                    Kranjskem od začetka 19. stoletja.</hi>
                                Ljubljana: Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, 2002;
                                Schmidt: <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike na
                                    Slovenskem II.</hi> and Andoljšek, Ivan: <hi rend="italic">Naš začetni bralni pouk in učbeniki zanj I.
                                    (1550</hi><hi rend="italic">–</hi><hi rend="italic">1869).</hi> Maribor: Dopisna delavska univerza Univerzum,
                                    1978.</note>
                        When working on textbooks from Prekmurje, we drew on the work of Ivan
                            Škafar. It should also be noted that in the case of Prekmurje the names
                            of the publishers are listed first, followed by the surname. Thus, we
                            followed the record that is in line with our standard, and not the
                            original order. We have also at all times standardized the records of
                            those publishing houses whose names did not derive from the personal
                            name of the publisher. The place of the first known edition is indicated
                            in the field "Publisher (first edition)." The places of publication of
                            all other editions are indicated in the field "Publisher (subsequent
                            editions)". In relation to writing years in parentheses, the same rules
                            apply as when citing titles and places of publication.
                    </p>
                    <p>In cases where the name of the publisher is unknown, the name of the
                            printer is given. In the rare cases where we have not been able to
                            identify even the latter, we provide information about the bookshops or
                            booksellers where the textbook was sold and related
                        information.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.6 Year of publication</head>
                    <p>In certain instances, we only have information about the year of
                            publication, but not other information about a textbook. In such cases,
                            the year of publication is provided only in the "Year of publication"
                            field, but not elsewhere. Therefore, in some places there is a
                            discrepancy between the years, which are listed in the other fields.
                            Although it is very likely that in such cases all other information was
                            also often the same – i.e., title, place, and publisher – this cannot be
                            stated with certainty.
                    </p>
                    <p>For textbooks that began to be published after 1869, we only indicated
                            the period of validity of the textbook and not each reprint separately,
                            since reprints of some textbooks were published almost every year, but
                            the content did not change.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.7 Data on the use of textbook material</head>
                    <p>The information about the purpose of the textbook material, which is
                            listed in the "Subject" field, is intended exclusively for the basic
                            orientation of the reader but cannot be the basis for a more detailed
                            analysis of the use of textbooks. In everyday practice, the use of
                            textbooks did not always correspond to their original purpose, in
                            addition, the names of some subjects and the subjects themselves changed
                            over time. For a more precise insight into the use of an individual
                            textbook, readers can help themselves with the bibliography listed in
                            the "Sources and bibliography" section. For the period after 1869, a
                            precise insight into the purpose of the approved textbooks is also
                            provided by the materials of the Ministry of Education. Links to
                            relevant material are also available in the "Sources and bibliography"
                            section.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3 Using the bibliography</head>
                <p>The bibliography of textbooks is located in the "Tabular display" tab, where
                        a table with basic data is displayed: Title of first edition, Author, Year,
                        Place (of first edition) and Subject. By clicking on the link in the title,
                        we open the full description of each textbook with links to digitized
                        material (if available).
                </p>
                <p>At the top left, you can change the displayed data on the "Column visibility"
                        button. By clicking on the title of each column, textbooks can also be
                        sorted by alphabet, year, etc.</p>
                <p>By moving through the pages, users can browse between textbooks or in the
                        search engine at the top right, they can browse all data, and at the bottom
                        of the table, search for basic data. At the top of the page, you can also
                        filter textbooks by year of publication and display textbooks published in
                        the selected period. </p>
                <p>The table can be exported in .csv, .xlsx and .pdf formats. If the data is
                        already filtered with the search engine, it will only export the displayed
                        textbooks, otherwise the entire table will be exported.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>3.1 Using the list of approved textbooks for the period between 1869
                            and 1918</head>
                    <p>In creating the database, we made extensive use of the Orders of the
                            Ministry of Education ("Verordnungsblatt des Ministeriums für Cultus und
                            Unterricht"). Since 1869, all approved textbooks and teaching aids have
                            been listed in the latter.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p> Žigon, Tanja, Almasy, Karin in Lovšin, Andrej: <hi rend="italic">Vloga in pomen prevajanja učbenikov v 19.
                                    stoletju: kulturnozgodovinski in jezikovni vidiki</hi>.
                                    Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete Univerze v
                                    Ljubljani, 2017, 46.
                            </p></note> In addition, from 1878 until the dissolution of the
                            Austria-Hungary (except in 1916 and 1918), overview lists of valid
                            approved textbooks for elementary schools and vocational secondary
                            schools (Bürgerschulen) were also published in the Orders of the
                            Ministry. Simultaneously with the annual lists of textbooks for
                            elementary schools and secondary vocational schools, separate lists of
                            teaching aids also began to be compiled. From 1884 onwards, overview
                            lists of approved textbooks for high schools and Realschulen were
                            published approximately every four years. 
                    </p>
                    <p>As part of the work with the Orders of the Ministry of Education, a
                            relatively extensive corpus of lists of approved textbooks and teaching
                            aids was created, which we decided to include separately in the final
                            version of the publication due to its potential usefulness for
                            researchers of the question under consideration. When transcribing the
                            titles, we have always faithfully followed the record in the Orders of
                            the Ministry of Education. The latter may differ slightly from the
                            actual titles (as a rule, these are minor typographical errors or
                            shortening of longer titles), but these differences do not, as a rule,
                            make it difficult to identify individual textbooks. In the following
                            lines, we will try to briefly outline the structure and potential
                            usefulness of the present corpus of lists. </p>
                    <p>The present corpus of lists of approved textbooks and teaching aids for
                            the period between 1869 and 1918 is compiled according to the following
                            key:</p>
                    <p>1. Included in the lists are textbooks and teaching aids for elementary
                            schools and secondary vocational schools, Gymnasia, Realschulen, and
                            girls' lyceums. Only material in the Slovene language is included, or
                            material that was specifically intended for classes in elementary
                            schools with the Slovene language of instruction. A problem arises
                            especially with teaching aids because it would probably not be too bold
                            to assume that many teaching aids, which were not written in Slovene or
                            were not specifically intended for classes in schools with the Slovene
                            language of instruction, were used for classes in schools with the
                            Slovene language of instruction. The limitation to Slovene language, for
                            example, also led to the fact that we did not include atlases and maps
                            of individual provinces in the present list if they were not published
                            in Slovene, but in some other language (as a rule, maps were published
                            in German and Italian languages).
                    </p>
                    <p>2. For the period between 1869 and 1877, the present list is based on the
                            lists "Alphabetisches Verzeichnis über Lehrbücher und Lehrmittel" and
                            "Verfügungen, betreffend Lehrbücher und Lehrmittel". These lists tell us
                            which textbooks were approved in a particular year, they contain
                            information about the author, title, location, publisher, year of
                            publication, the environment in which the textbook is intended to be
                            used (as a rule, these are individual types of educational institutions,
                            less often for provincial framework), the type of textbook material and
                            the level for which the textbook was intended, but they do not provide a
                            comprehensive list of valid textbooks for an individual year. As already
                            mentioned, when collecting and digitizing secondary school textbook
                            material, we limited ourselves to the first four years (see point 1
                            regarding exceptions). All lists of this type are identified in the
                            present corpus of lists by the key "[Year]_Vf._Lehrbücher_mittel". We
                            kept this type of lists for a later period as well, but due to the
                            ever-increasing amount of approved material, we stopped compiling them
                            starting from 1900. Since 1878 and 1884, all textbooks have also been
                            listed in overview lists of approved textbooks. We have again prepared
                            such lists for the period from 1915 onwards. Namely, after 1915,
                            overview lists of approved textbooks for Gymnasia and Realschulen were
                            no longer compiled, and after 1917, the same thing happened with
                            overview lists of textbooks for elementary schools and vocational
                            secondary schools. The information in the present lists is somewhat more
                            comprehensive than those which can be obtained from the overview lists,
                            but the search for information in the sections "Alphabetisches
                            Verzeichnis über Lehrbücher und Lehrmittel" and "Verfügungen, betreffend
                            Lehrbücher und Lehrmittel" with the help of the corresponding indexes
                            and data, provided by overview lists of textbook material, is relatively
                            straightforward.
                    </p>
                    <p>3. As stated, for the period from 1878 onwards (with the exception of
                            1916 and 1918), overview lists of textbooks for elementary schools and
                            vocational secondary schools or higher primary schools, are available
                            for each year, which allow a good overview of the changes in the
                            structure of the textbook material and could be an interesting subject
                            of study. All the mentioned lists are marked by the key
                            "[Year]_Lehrbücherverzeichnis_V_B". The same applies to overview lists
                            of textbooks for Gymnasia and Realschulen. These were compiled at longer
                            intervals and are available for the years 1884, 1888, 1892, 1896, 1900,
                            1904, 1909, and 1915. The lists also include material for upper
                            secondary school program, as we considered it reasonable due to
                            transparency and the possibility of further analysis of the lists. The
                            material can in principle be separated from each other without too much
                            difficulty. All the mentioned lists are marked by the key
                            "[Year]_Lehrbücherverzeichnis_G_R".</p>
                    <p>4. Simultaneously with the annual review lists of approved textbooks for
                            elementary schools and vocational secondary schools, separate lists of
                            teaching aids also began to be maintained. Despite the fact that these
                            are also available for the entire period between 1878 and 1918 (except
                            for 1916 and 1918), we did not compile them for each year separately,
                            but in intervals for 1878; 1880; 1890; 1900; 1910; 1917. All the
                            mentioned lists are marked by the key
                            "[Year]_Lehrmittelverzeichnis".</p>
                    <p>An excel file for exporting the <hi rend="bold ">list of approved
                            textbooks</hi> will be available here.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4 Sources and bibliography</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Andoljšek, Ivan: <hi rend="italic">Naš začetni bralni pouk in
                            učbeniki zanj I. (1550–1869)</hi>. Maribor: Dopisna delavska
                            univerza Univerzum, 1978.
                    </item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">Deželni zakonik in vladni list za kranjsko
                            kronovino</hi> 25, št. 8 (June 26, 1873). Available at the Digital
                            Library of Slovenia - dLib: <ref target="http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:DOC-B3JVUCGN">http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:DOC-B3JVUCGN</ref>
                            (June 23, 2023).</item>
                    <item>Dular, Anja: <hi rend="italic">Živeti od knjig: zgodovina
                            knjigotrštva na Kranjskem od začetka 19. stoletja</hi>. Ljubljana:
                            Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, 2002. </item>
                    <item>Grafenauer, Bogo: "Podržavljenje šolstva in splošna šolska obveznost."
                            In: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Slovencev</hi>, ed. Čepič Zdenko et. al.
                            Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1979, 375–381.</item>
                    <item>Schmidt, Vlado: <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike
                            na Slovenskem I. (Od naselitve do 1805</hi>). Ljubljana: Delavska
                            enotnost, 1988.
                    </item>
                    <item>Schmidt, Vlado: <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike
                            na Slovenskem II. (1805–1848).</hi> Ljubljana: Državna založba
                            Slovenije, 1964.</item>
                    <item>Schmidt, Vlado: <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina šolstva in pedagogike
                            na Slovenskem III. (1848–1870).</hi> Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost,
                            1988.
                    </item>
                    <item>Šumrada, Janez: "Poglavitne poteze napoleonske politike v Ilirskih
                            provincah."
                        <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 61, No. 1–2 (2007):
                            75–84.</item>
                    <item>Žigon, Tanja; Almasy, Karin and Lovšin, Andrej: <hi rend="italic">Vloga in pomen prevajanja učbenikov v 19. stoletju: kulturnozgodovinski
                            in jezikovni vidiki.</hi>
                        Ljubljana: <hi rend="background(white)">Znanstvena založba
                            Filozofske fakultete Univerze v Ljubljani</hi>, 2017.<lb/><ref target="https://doi.org/10.4312/9789612379773"><hi rend="underline color(1155CC)">https://doi.org/10.4312/9789612379773</hi></ref></item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>